<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter>
<title>First steps</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Quick start</title>
<para>The classic introduction for compiler tools is a calculator to compute expressions like
<literal>68/2+8</literal> <!-- 42 -->. Mork provides a calculator example
<indexterm><primary>calculator</primary></indexterm>, you can compile and run it as follows:
<programlisting>
  cd mork/examples
  CLASSPATH=.
  javac -g calc/*.java
  mork calc/Calc.map
  java calc.Main
</programlisting>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Example</title>
<para>This chapter is built around an example called <literal>command</literal>
<indexterm><primary>command</primary></indexterm>. The above calculator example is not suitable
because it demonstrates the most basic features only. <literal>command</literal> is simple enough
to serve as an introduction and it is as complex as necessary to demonstrate the important
features.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Overview</title>
<para>The next section explains how to compile and run <literal>command</literal> without digging
into the sources. This is followed by various sections that pick the interesting aspects of
<literal>command</literal> and explain them in more detail. Note that this chapter is an
introduction, exhaustive coverage follows in the remaining chapters.</para></formalpara>

<sect1>
<title>Get going</title>

<formalpara>
<title><literal>command</literal></title>
<para><literal>command</literal> adds GUI front-ends to command line tools like
<literal>javac</literal>, <literal>jar</literal>, or <literal>mork</literal>. To do so, the form of
valid command lines is described in a command file. A command file describing Java's
<literal>jar</literal> command line tool is shown in the listing below. The description consists
of three things:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>a command name: <literal>create jar</literal></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>variable declarations:
    <literal>jar</literal> for the name of the jar file to create
    and <literal>dir</literal> for the directory to be zipped.</para>
    </listitem>
  <listitem><para>a command line: <literal>run "jar cvf " + jar + " " + dir;</literal>
    defines how to combine variable values into the command line to invoke
    <literal>jar</literal></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Note: To keep things simple, only a fraction of <literal>jar</literal>'s functionality is
provided. Most notably, you can create jar file only, extracting data is not available.
</para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title>jar command file</title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "tests", "jar.cf"), Xml.HASH_HEAD) }: -->
&jarText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Front-ends</title>
<para>Running <literal>command</literal> on a command file opens a window that provides a
front-end to the respective command line tool. The front-end has fields for
all variables declared in the command file and provides two buttons to
start the command or to cancel without running the command. The following
figure shows the front-end corresponding to the above command file.
</para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title>jar command screen shot</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="jarCF.jpg" format="JPG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Source code</title>
<para><literal>command</literal>'s source code is located in <literal>examples/command</literal>,
the contents of this directory is listed below. It contains mostly Java files, Most of the Java
files will be touched in the course of this chapter. Maybe the two most important Java files
are <literal>Main.java</literal> which implements the overall logic and
<literal>Command.java</literal> which defines the <literal>command.Command</literal> class. The
largest Java files are <literal>Console.java</literal> (implementing a console window
for command output) and <literal>Frontend.java</literal> (implementing the initial Swing
dialog). </para></formalpara>
<!-- TODO: javadoc link. -->

<figure>
<title>Source files</title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.ls(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command"), new String[] { "*.java", "*.map", "*.grm" }) }: -->
         command.grm    1108 bytes
        Command.java    1104 bytes
        Console.java    4670 bytes
       Constant.java     644 bytes
   Declarations.java    1785 bytes
     Expression.java     530 bytes
        Failure.java     557 bytes
       Frontend.java    2823 bytes
           Line.java    1021 bytes
           Main.java    1217 bytes
          Mapper.map     947 bytes
      Reference.java     896 bytes
       Variable.java    1061 bytes

<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<para>Besides Java files, the source directory contains a grammar file
<literal>command.grm</literal> and a mapper file <literal>Mapper.map</literal>. The grammar file
defines the syntax of command files and the mapper file defines how to map a command files into an
instance of <literal>command.Command</literal>.</para>

<formalpara>
<title><literal>Javadoc</literal></title>
<para>To have a closer look at the Java files you might want to generate the
<literal>javadoc</literal> documentation for examples ...
<programlisting>
  cd examples
  mkdir command/javadoc
  javadoc -d command/javadoc -sourcepath . command
</programlisting></para></formalpara>


<formalpara>
<title>Compiling</title>
<para>To compile <literal>command</literal>, run <literal>javac</literal> on the Java files and
<literal>mork</literal> on the mapper file:
<programlisting>
  cd examples
  CLASSPATH=.
  javac -g command/*.java
  mork command/Mapper.map
</programlisting>
Mork translates both the mapper file and the grammar file into several Java class files.
Note that mapper files contains a reference to <literal>command.grm</literal>. Therefore, only
the file <literal>Mapper.map</literal> has to be specified when calling <literal>mork</literal>.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Running</title>
<para>Running <literal>command</literal> takes one argument: the command file to be processed. You
can create your own command file or you can use one of the sample command files in the tests
directory. Run the <literal>jar</literal> command mentioned above as follows:
<programlisting>
  cd examples/command/tests
  java command.Main jar.cf
</programlisting>
</para></formalpara>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Overall logic</title>

<figure>
<title>command.Main</title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "Main.java"), Xml.JAVA_HEAD) }: -->
&MainText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<para><literal>Main.java</literal> defines the <literal>main</literal> method which implements the
overall logic of <literal>command</literal>. <literal>main</literal> demonstrates the typical steps
to use a mapper: <orderedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>Instantiate the mapper class generated by Mork:
<programlisting>
    mapper = new Mapper("command.Mapper");
</programlisting>
  </para></listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Use the mapper object to read the command file specified on the command line:
<programlisting>
    tmp = mapper.run(args[0])
</programlisting>
  </para></listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Running the mapper turns the command file into an instances of command.Command:
<programlisting>
    command = (Command) tmp[0];
</programlisting></para></listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Run the command, i.e. open the front-end window and execute the command line built
  from the end-user's input.
<programlisting>
    command.run();
</programlisting></para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Grammar files</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Grammar files</title>
<para><literal>command.grm</literal> defines the syntax of command files. A grammar file has a
scanner section and a parser section.</para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title><literal>command.grm</literal></title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "command.grm"), Xml.HASH_HEAD) }: -->
&commandText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Syntax</title>
<para>The syntax is specified in terms of symbols. Scanner and parser section give a list of rules.
A rule has a left hand side and a right hand side, separated by <literal>::=</literal>. It defines
a symbol by specifying how the symbol on the left hand side is composed of symbols on the right
hand side. Running the mapper creates a syntax tree according to these rules, where each node
represents a symbol. Usually, the leafs of the syntax tree are defined in the scanner section,
whereas the inner nodes are define in the parser section. The first rule in the parser section
defines the root node of the syntax tree.</para></formalpara>

<!-- TODO
<figure>
<title>command file analyzing</title>
<mediaobject>
<textobject>
TODO: Picture with characters, syntax tree and objects
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
-->


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Mapper files</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Mapper files</title>
<para><literal>Mapper.map</literal> defines how to turn command files into instances of
<literal>command.Command</literal>. Running the mapper reads a command file, checks for
the appropriate syntax (defined in the grammar file) and maps the file into an instance of
<literal>command.Command</literal></para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title><literal>Mapper.map</literal></title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "Mapper.map"), Xml.HASH_HEAD) }: -->
&MapperText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Mapping</title>
<para>A mapper file is comprised of a list of attributes. The basic form of an attribute
<indexterm><primary>attribute</primary></indexterm> associates a symbol (on the left hand side)
with a constructor (on the right hand side). Whenever the specified symbol is found in some input
stream, the associated constructor is triggered. Here are two attributes used in the
<literal>command</literal> application.
<programlisting>
Command         => Command;
String          => BuiltIn.parseString;
</programlisting>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Runtime</title>
<para>At runtime, a mapper first creates a syntax tree of the input stream. If this step is
successful (i.e. there are no syntax errors), the mapper walks through the nodes of the syntax
tree and invokes the constructors associated for the respective symbol. Example 1: The symbol
<literal>Command</literal> triggers invocation of the constructor <literal>Command</literal> which
results in an new instance of the class <literal>command.Command</literal>. Example 2: The symbol
<literal>Identifier</literal> triggers invocation of the constructor
<literal>BuildIn.parseString</literal> which results in a new instance of the class
<literal>java.lang.String</literal>. A mapper returns the object(s) created for the root node. In
the <literal>command</literal> example, this is a <literal>command.Command</literal> object.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Constructors</title>
<para>The right hand side of an attribute specifies a constructor. A constructor
<indexterm><primary>constructor</primary></indexterm> may be a Java constructor (e.g.
<literal>command.Command</literal>), a Java method (e.g.
<literal>org.qooxdoo.sushi.semantics.BuiltIn.parseString</literal>), or an internal constructor.
Thus, the term constructor is used in a more generalized meaning.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Internal constructors</title>
<para>A common requirement for symbols like <literal>Identifier</literal> is to access
the actual input matched by the symbol. Example: the symbol <literal>Identifier</literal>
might match the input <literal>jar</literal>. For this purpose, Mork provides internal
constructors.<indexterm><primary>internal constructors</primary></indexterm>
<literal>command</literal> use the internal constructor <literal>[text]</literal> to
access the actual input matched by the symbol. (There are more internal constructors
besides <literal>[text]</literal>, but in most cases, <literal>[text]</literal> is all you need).
<programlisting>
Identifier      => [text];
Literal         => [text];
</programlisting>
Note: internal constructors are restricted to symbols defined in the scanner section; associating
them with symbols defined in the parser section results in an error.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Import and package</title>
<para>Import and package declarations in the mapper file are similar to their Java
counter-parts. As demonstrated by the attributes for <literal>Command</literal> and
<literal>String</literal> symbols, imported classes can be specified without
a package name. However, there is one important difference from Java's
import declaration: all classes have to be imported explicitly. Example: all classes from
<literal>command</literal> are explicitly imported, even though the mapper resides in
the same package. Similarly, classes from <literal>java.lang</literal> have to be imported
explicitly. Explicitly also means that Mork does not provide something like
<literal>import foo.*</literal>.</para></formalpara>


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Visibility</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Argument passing</title>
<para>In the previous section, you have seen how to associate symbols with constructors
in order to create objects. Constructors take arguments. How do you define the arguments
passed to a constructor? The answer is visibility. If you now other compiler tools it might take
some time to get used to the visibility idea. But it's the feature that makes mapper files simple
and powerful.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Java argument passing</title>
<para>Let's have a look at argument passing in Java. Consider the following Java fragment,
where <literal>name</literal>, <literal>decls</literal> and <literal>line</literal> are
variables holding appropriate values:
<programlisting>
  new Command(name, decls, line)
</programlisting>
This expression invokes the constructor of the <literal>command.Command</literal> class. The
arguments passed to the constructor are specified by an argument list. In Java, an argument
list defines the arguments passed to a constructor. OK, that's obvious. But read on ...
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Mork argument passing</title>
<para>In Mork, visibility defines the arguments passed to a constructor. In some sense,
visibility turns Java's argument lists upside down: argument lists are tied to the constructor
and kind of pull arguments into the constructor. In contrast, visibility is tied to an argument
and kind of pushes it toward an constructor. This is illustrated in the graphic below.
</para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title>Argument passing</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="passing.jpg" format="JPG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Visibility</title>
<para>Each attribute has a visibility which defines the constructors the attribute is passed
to as an argument. <indexterm><primary>visibility</primary></indexterm>Visibility can be defined
explicitly and implicitly. Look at the listing below, it shows two attribute definitions from
<literal>command</literal>'s map file. Visibility of the <literal>Declarations</literal> attribute
is defined explicitly by a colon <literal>":"</literal> and two paths <literal>\\Command</literal>
and <literal>\\Command//Reference</literal>. In contrast, the <literal>Command</literal> attribute
has implicit visibility since there is no explicit visibility defined.</para></formalpara>

<programlisting>
Command         => Command;
Declarations    => Declarations:
                     > \\Command
                     > \\Command//Reference;
</programlisting>

<formalpara>
<title>Implicit visibility</title>
<para>An attribute with implicit visibility is passed to the constructor attached to the nearest
symbol in the syntax tree above. Example: <literal>command.Command</literal>'s constructor
takes three arguments: two Strings, an instance of <literal>command.Declarations</literal> and an
instance of <literal>command.Line</literal>. All of the attributes involved
(<literal>String</literal>, <literal>Declarations</literal>, and <literal>Line</literal>) have
implicit visibility, and the nearest constructor in the syntax tree above is
<literal>command.Command</literal>. Consequently, these are the attributes passed
<literal>command.Command</literal>. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Explicit visibility</title>
<para>Implicit visibility is appropriate in most situations. Explicit visibility enters the scene
if an object has to be passed to a constructor other than the constructor in the syntax tree
above. Explicit visibility is defined by a list of paths. Attributes with explicit visibility are
passed to all constructors defined by the paths. The need for explicit visibility typically arises
when resolving identifiers -- which will be studied in the respective section below.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Argument order</title>
<para>Visibility declarations do not define the argument order. If two attributes are visible to a
given constructor, which attribute is passed first? Basically, Mork computes the argument order by
iterating the list of formal arguments, passing the left-most attribute assignable to the current
formal arguments. Consider <literal>command.Command</literal>'s constructor: the formal argument
list is <literal>(String name, String description, Declarations decls, Line line)</literal>. The
list of visible attributes are <literal>String</literal>, <literal>String</literal>,
<literal>Declarations</literal> and <literal>Line</literal>. Note that this list is ordered
according to the order of attributes in the syntax tree (which mostly resembles the grammar rule
<literal>Command ::= "command" String ":" String Declarations "{" Line "}" ;</literal>).
<literal>String</literal> argument occurs twice since the <literal>String</literal> symbols has
two occurrences in the grammar rule.  Argument ordering is performed as follows: The left-most
attribute which is assignable to <literal>name</literal> is the first <literal>String</literal>
attribute, thus it is assigned to <literal>name</literal>. After this, the second
<literal>String</literal> attribute is passed since it is the only remaining attribute which is
assignable to the formal argument <literal>String description</literal>. Similarly, the attribute
<literal>Declarations</literal> is assigned to the formal argument <literal>decls</literal> and the
attribute <literal>Line</literal> is assigned to the formal argument <literal>line</literal>.
</para></formalpara>

<para>
Note that the argument order is computed at compile-time, i.e. when translating the map file.
An error is reported if there is no valid argument order. </para>

<formalpara>
<title>List arguments</title>
<para>The attribute <literal>Variable</literal> has default visibility, thus it is added to the
argument lists passed to the <literal>command.Declarations</literal> constructor. The type of this
argument is <literal>Variable*</literal> where <literal>*</literal> indicates a list argument.
<literal>Variable</literal> is a list argument since a given syntax tree might have any number of
Variable attributes. A List arguments is assignable to <literal>java.util.List</literal> or arrays
of the respective base type.  TODO: more about </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Option arguments</title>
<para>TODO: change command to include an example for optional arguments. TODO: more about
optional arguments.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Argument merging</title>
<para>Alternative arguments are merged. Example <literal>Constant</literal> and
<literal>Reference</literal>.  TODO: more about this. </para></formalpara>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Error handling </title>

<formalpara>
<title>Errors</title>
<para><literal>command</literal>'s <literal>main</literal> method uses <literal>Mapper.run</literal>
to read command files. This method reports syntax errors and semantic errors to System.err. A syntax
error is reported whenever the syntax of the input stream read by the mapper does not match the
syntax specified in the syntax file underlying this mapper. Semantic errors are reported whenever
one of the constructors throws a checked exception.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Semantic errors</title>
<para><literal>command</literal> makes sure that variable names are unique. If two variable have
the same name, a semantic error is reported. To see this message, just duplicate the declaration
for the <literal>jar</literal> variable in <literal>tests/jar.cf</literal> and run
<literal>command</literal> on it:
<programlisting>
examples/command > cat tests/jar.cf
command "create jar"
    jar: "jar file";
    jar: "jar file";
    dir: "directory";
{
    run "jar cvf " + jar + " " + dir;
}
examples/command > java command.Main tests/jar.cf
tests/jar.cf:2:5: semantic error: duplicate variable name: jar
examples/command >
</programlisting>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Defining</title>
<para>Defining semantic errors<indexterm><primary>semantic error</primary></indexterm> is straight
forward: check for the error situation in the appropriate constructor and, if a problem is
detected, throw a checked exception. Whenever a mapper encounters a checked exception, it issues a
semantic error message, reporting the current source positions and the string obtained from
<literal>Exception.getMessage()</literal>. The current source position is the position of syntax
tree node, the constructor was invoked for.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Duplicate Identifier</title>
<para><literal>command</literal>'s semantic error <literal>duplicate variable name</literal> is
realized in the file <literal>Declarations.java</literal> listed below. The constructor takes an
argument with all variables declared in a given command file. After storing these variables in a
member variable, <literal>checkDuplicates</literal> is invoked to look for a name that is used more
than once. If a duplicate name is found, it throws a <literal>Failure</literal> exception.
The <literal>Failure</literal> class extends <literal>java.lang.Exception</literal>, thus it is
a checked exception. When reporting this error, the exception message
<literal>duplicate variable name</literal> is used to describe the problem. The position
reported is the position of the <literal>Declarations</literal> symbol. </para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title><literal>Declarations.java</literal></title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "Declarations.java"), Xml.JAVA_HEAD) }: -->
&DeclarationsText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<para>The next section includes another example for semantic errors.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Resolving identifiers</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Meta</title>
<para>Resolving identifiers can be seen as an advanced topic, but it is a common task within
applications that use Mork. Almost every compiler or interpreter resolves variable names
in one way or another.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Example</title>
<para>The <literal>command</literal> example has to resolve identifiers to evaluate the command line
specified in a command file. Consider the jar command file listed in the first section. It includes
the command line
<programlisting>
    run "jar cvf " + jar + " " + dir;
</programlisting>
To evaluate this line, <literal>command</literal> has to find the variables referenced by the
identifiers <literal>jar</literal> and <literal>dir</literal>. This is called identifier resolution.
<indexterm><primary>identifier resolution</primary></indexterm>
<literal>command</literal>'s identifier resolution is implemented in the files
<literal>Line.java</literal> and <literal>Reference.java</literal>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Line objects</title>
<para>Before digging into identifier resolution, I have to explain the <literal>Line</literal>
class. See the listing below. Instances of this class represent command lines like
<literal>run "jar cvf " + jar + " " + dir;</literal>. A <literal>Line</literal> is characterized
by an array of exceptions. This array is passed to the constructor and stored in the field
<literal>exceptions</literal>. The command line <literal>run "jar cvf " + jar + " " + dir;</literal>
is an array of four expressions: two constants (<literal>"jar cvf "</literal> and
<literal>" "</literal>) and two variable references (<literal>jar</literal> and
<literal>dir</literal>). Constants are represented by instances of
<literal>command.Constant</literal> and variables are presented by instances of
<literal>command.Reference</literal>. Both classes extend <literal>command.Expression</literal> and
thus have an <literal>eval</literal> method. The whole purpose of <literal>Line</literal> is to
provide another <literal>eval</literal> method; <literal>Line</literal>'s <literal>eval</literal>
is used in <literal>Command.execute</literal> to compute the string which is used to launch
an operating system process. <literal>Line</literal>'s <literal>eval</literal> method simply
evaluates all expressions and concatenates the results. </para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title><literal>Line.java</literal></title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "Line.java"), Xml.JAVA_HEAD) }: -->
&LineText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>References</title>
<para><literal>command.Reference</literal> is shown in the listing below. A reference is nothing
but a pointer to the variable it refers to. When asked to evaluate itself, it just returns the
current value of the variable. The interesting part of the <literal>Reference</literal> class is
its constructor. The constructor expects two variables, a declarations object and an identifier.
What happens inside is straight forward: the declarations object is searched for the identifier.
If the is a variable with the specified name, it is stored in the <literal>var</literal>
field and the identifier resolution has succeeded. Otherwise, a semantic error
<literal>unkown identifier</literal> is issued by throwing an exception. </para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title><literal>Reference.java</literal></title>
<programlisting>
<!-- §{xml.includeSource(Files.join(Config.HOME, "examples", "command", "Reference.java"), Xml.JAVA_HEAD) }: -->
&ReferenceText;
<!-- §. -->
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Argument passing</title>
<para>The constructor of <literal>command.Reference</literal> expects two arguments:
a <literal>Declarations</literal> object and a <literal>String</literal> object. As explained
in the visibility section above, the arguments passed to a constructor are determined by visibility
definitions. The following visibility definitions are relevant here:
<programlisting>
Declarations    => Declarations:
                     > \\Command
                     > \\Command//Reference;
Identifier      => String;
</programlisting>
The <literal>Identifier</literal> attribute has implicit visibility. Consequently, it is passed
to the nearest constructor in the syntax tree above - which is <literal>command.Reference</literal>.
The <literal>Declarations</literal> attribute has explicit visibility, defined by two paths.
The first path <literal>\\Command</literal> specifies to pass the attribute up to
<literal>command.Command</literal>'s constructor - which is not relevant here. The second path
<literal>\\Command//Reference</literal> specifies to pass the attribute up to the
<literal>Command</literal> symbol and from there down to any <literal>Reference</literal>
constructor. Thus, <literal>command.Command</literal> obtains both a <literal>String</literal> and
a <literal>Declarations</literal> object and all it's arguments are satisfied.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Paths</title>
<para>In general, a path specifies a way through the syntax tree. <literal>\\</literal> passes an
attribute up in the syntax tree until the specified symbol is found, and <literal>//</literal>
passes an attribute down until the specified symbol is found.</para></formalpara>

<para>TODO: some words about optional arguments and lists of arguments.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What's next</title>

<para>This chapter introduced the most important features. There are several ways
to go on now:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <formalpara><title>Extend the <literal>command</literal> example</title>
  <para>Interesting stuff is missing in <literal>command</literal>:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Beautified dialogs</para></listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>More input elements like browse buttons or check boxes, e.g. to switch between
      creating a jar file and extracting data from a jar file. </para></listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Instead of launching an operating system process, a command could invoke
      static Java methods using reflection.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist></para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Study more examples</title>
  <para>Have a look at the examples directory. Both the interpreter and the compiler
  example are more complex than <literal>command</literal>.</para></formalpara>
  </listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Start a new application</title>
  <para>This is probably the most challenging way to continue. In particular, visibility
  declarations are more difficult than you might expect from looking at examples that run out of
  the box. In addition, the documentation in the remaining chapters is still incomplete. In general,
  I suggest starting new applications with a small grammar and just few classes you map to. If the
  small mapper work, continue by adding a single class and growing the grammar/mapping accordingly.
  Caution: if you first develop the complete grammar, then implement all your classes and then try
  to define a mapping, its much more difficult to solve visibility problems.
  </para>
  </formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Go on reading</title>
  <para>The remaining chapter in this manual provide in depth information about Mork.
  In my opinion it is more appropriate to just start using Mork an come back later.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

</chapter>
