<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

<sect1>
<title>Preface</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Prerequisites</title>
<para>This manual assumes knowledge about Java and some understanding of
regular expressions and context-free grammars.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Status</title>
<para>Mork is developed in my spare time. I consider Mork as beta code.
It has been tested for Mork itself (Mork is bootstrapped) and the example
applications - and nothing else. The syntax grammar part is stable. The
mapping part slowly matures. The XML syntax part is unstable. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Conventions</title>
<para>The following font conventions are used throughout this document
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>A <literal>typewriter font</literal> indicates example code or shell commands.
    </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>An <emphasis>italic font</emphasis> indicates that the given term is defined
    in the respective sentence. TODO: not completed yet.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>License</title>
<para><indexterm><primary>license</primary></indexterm>Mork is licensed under the terms of the GNU
Lesser General Public License. It is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE. For a copy of this license, see the file <literal>license.txt</literal>
which is part of the distribution. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Contact</title>
<para><indexterm><primary>contact</primary></indexterm><indexterm><primary>feedback</primary>
</indexterm>Please send your feedback to <email>michael.hartmeier@1und1.de</email>! Mork has a web page
at <ulink url="http://mork.sourceforge.net/">mork.sourceforge.net</ulink>
</para></formalpara>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Overview</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Applications</title>
<para><emphasis>Mork</emphasis><indexterm significance="preferred"><primary>Mork</primary>
</indexterm> is a compiler tool
for Java. Its purpose similar to ANTLR, JavaCC (and jjTree), JLex &amp; CUP, or SableCC. Mork can
be used for <emphasis>applications</emphasis><indexterm significance="preferred">
<primary>applications</primary></indexterm> that process input streams, e.g.
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><formalpara><title>calculators</title>
  <para>computing expressions</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>pretty printers</title>
  <para>formatting program sources</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>interpreters</title>
  <para>executing scripts</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>compilers</title>
  <para>translating programs</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>tools like make</title>
  <para>implement some kind of command language</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>application configuration</title>
  <para>reading configuration files (e.g. Tomcat's <literal>server.xml</literal> file
  or manifest file for <literal>jar</literal>)
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Mapping</title>
<para>Applications use Mork to map<indexterm><primary>mapping</primary></indexterm> input
streams into Java objects. Example 1: In a calculator application, Mork maps the input
<literal>17+5*7-10</literal> into a number object <literal>42</literal>. Example 2: In an
interpreter application, Mork maps a script file into Java objects like statements and expressions.
The underlying statement and expression classes are defined by the application, they usually have
methods like <literal>execute</literal> and <literal>eval</literal> that implement the actual
execution if the script. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Development</title>
<para>Developing an application with Mork centers around the mapper concept
<indexterm><primary>mapper</primary></indexterm>. This is outlined in the figure below. The
application is defined by three kinds of source files: (1) A syntax file defining the structure of
the input stream, (2) a mapper file that defines how to map input streams with this syntax into
Java objects, and (3) Java files defining the objects the input stream is mapped to. The application
is compiled into Java class files by running a Java compiler on the Java files and my running Mork
on the mapper file. At runtime, the application instantiates the mapper class and runs it on input
streams in order to map them into Java objects. </para></formalpara>

<figure>
<title>Development</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="development.jpg" format="JPG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Terminology</title>
<para>In this document, the term application<indexterm><primary>applications</primary></indexterm>
denotes an application that uses Mork. The term user <indexterm><primary>user</primary></indexterm>
refers to the developer who uses Mork to write an application; user does not refer to the person
using the application. This manual forms the user documentation for Mork.
<!-- most of the sentences sound better with "user"; "user guide" is just one example -->
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Outline</title>
<para>The next two chapters form a kind of user's guide, they describe how to install Mork
(chapter 2) and how to get going (3). The remaining chapter are written more like a reference.
Everything is centered around mappers: how to define the syntax of a mapper (4), how to define
the mapper itself (5), how to translate a mapper (6) and how to invoke a mapper from your
application (7). The last chapter (8) contains notes about example applications and the
implementation of Mork. </para></formalpara>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Features</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Mapper</title>
  <para>Applications use a mapper as a black box: they just run it on some input stream to get
  their objects instantiated. This is like de-serializing objects from file with arbitrary syntax
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Mapping</title>
  <para>An attribute is defined my simply associating symbols with constructors. A set of
  attributes defines a mapper. </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Visibility</title>
  <para>Visibility declarations can be used to make attributes available to almost any location
  in the syntax tree. </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Scanner</title>
  <para>Unicode support, scanner modes, and the usual regular expression operators.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Parser</title>
  <para>LALR(1) parsers and regular expression operators for grammar
  rules: EBNF and more.</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Attribution</title>
  <para>Well-defined attribute grammars: Any number of synthesized and
  inherited attributes.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>No embedded code</title>
  <para>Clean separation of syntax and semantics: syntax goes into
    the specification file, semantics into Java files.
    </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>True compiler</title>
  <para>Mork generates class file, not Java code: no Java-compile step is needed.
    </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Class file package</title>
  <para>To generate Java class files. Includes features like automatic
    stack size computation.</para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Examples</title>
  <para>Mork includes an interpreter example, a compiler example that
    generates bytecode, and a Java parser example.
    </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara>
  <title>Positional error messages</title>
  <para>Throwing an exception reports the current position and the
  exception message.</para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

</chapter>
