<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter>
<title>Syntax files</title>

<formalpara><title>Syntax files</title>
<para>This chapter is about syntax files. A syntax file defines the structure of
an input stream. Mork reads syntax files when processing a mapper file. Mork supports
two types of syntax: grammar syntax and XML syntax. Grammar syntax is based on
context-free syntax, it allows to define the syntax of most programming languages.
XML syntax is more restricted, it allows to define the syntax of XML files only.
Examples: Java has a grammar syntax, whereas DocBook has an XML syntax.
</para></formalpara>

<para>When writing applications, you have to choose between grammar syntax or XML syntax.
Here are some pros and cons for using XML syntax:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Pro: XML syntax is easy to learn or grasp from examples.
    </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Pro: It easy for applications to read you file because
    the appropriate XML tools are quite common.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Cons: XML is verbose and thus hard to read and write.
    This is not a problems for simple configuration file. But the
    more complex the XML file is, the harder it is to work with them.
    If you want humans to use XML files without special XML editors, your syntax should
    not be more complex than Apache Ant files (<literal>build.xml</literal>).
    If you want to see examples for more complex syntax, have a look
    XML stylesheets (XSL files) XML schema definitions (XSD files). In my
    opinion, these files form a bad examples, they are too verbose
    (and they even use "embedded" syntax for paths).
    </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>


<sect1>
<title>Grammar syntax</title>

<para>Grammar syntax is defined by a list of BNF-style rules. The list of rules is divided
into a parser section defining a pushdown automaton and a scanner section defining a finite
automaton. Grammar syntax is defined by grammar files.</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Naming convention</title>
<para>My naming convention for grammar files is as follows. The base name of
a grammar files is the name of the language specified in the file. The first
letter is lower case because that's consistent with dtd files and I prefer
lowercase names (even though this conflicts with Java's naming convention
for class names). The file name extension is <literal>.grm</literal> (all
lower case on every platform). Examples: <literal>java.grm</literal> for a Java
syntax. <literal>config.grm</literal> for the syntax of configuration files.
</para></formalpara>

<sect2>
<title>Overall structure</title>

<figure>
<title>Overall structure</title>
<programlisting>
Grammar             ::= Parser Scanner ;
Parser              ::= "[" "PARSER" "]" Rule+ ;
Scanner             ::= "[" "SCANNER" "]" Priorities WhiteOpt Rule* ;
Priorities          ::= UsePriorities | NoPriorities;
UsePriorities       ::= ;
NoPriorities        ::= "nopriorities;";
WhiteOpt            ::= ("white" "=" SymbolSet ";")? ;
SymbolSet           ::= ( Symbol ("," Symbol)* )? ;
</programlisting>
</figure>

<para>Start symbol of a grammar file is <literal>Grammar</literal>.</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Sections</title>
<para>A grammar file is divided into a parser section and a scanner
section. Sections have a header and a body. Headers adjusts global options
that apply to the whole body. The body is comprised of a set of rules. The rules within
both sections should proceed from large element to small elements, i.e. the
start symbol should be specified first, and terminal symbols should be
specified last. For that reason, the parser section precedes the scanner
section. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Parser section</title>
<para>The parser section defines the context-free structure of the input
stream. The section header identifies that parser section, no other options
are given. The section body specifies a list of rules, each of them comprised
of a symbol and a regular expression. These rules define the context-free
grammar that parses the input stream. The symbol of the first rule is the
start symbol of the grammar. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Scanner section</title>
<para>The scanner section defines the regular structure of the input
stream. The section header specifies white symbols, i.e. terminal symbols
to be removed from the input stream; these symbols are never returned to
the parser. Typical examples for white symbols are white space and comments.
The section body is comprised of a list of rules, each of them comprised of
a symbol and a regular expression.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Priorities</title>
<para>Specifies how to resolve conflicts between two terminals that match
the same input. A typical example is a keyword like <literal>begin</literal> and an
<literal>identifier</literal> terminal that also matches the input <literal>begin</literal>.
Traditionally, scanner generators use priorities to resolve this conflict: if the input
<literal>begin</literal> is found, the terminal defined first will be matched. This behavior
is useful for programming languages like Java where a keyword is not a valid identifier:
just define the keywords before the identifier and you scanner will never match an identifier
if there is also a keyword for the respective input.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>No Priorities</title>
<para>Specify <literal>nopriorities</literal> if you don't want to resolve scanner
conflicts based on their priority. In this case, Mork will try to resolve the conflict
by choosing appropriate scanner modes. Example: in XML, the <literal>Name</literal>
terminal conflicts with the <literal>Nmtoken</literal>. This conflict must not be solved
by priorities because the scanner needs to match both terminals. Mork ensures that
no parser state can shift both terminals and adds both terminals to different scanner modes.
The generated parser automatically switches it's scanner into the mode that matches all
terminals currently shiftable.</para></formalpara>


</sect2>


<sect2>
<title>Symbols</title>

<para>The syntax of input streams is defined in terms of symbols. Any symbol
has a language which is defined by the parser and scanner section. A language
is a set of strings. The set might be empty, it might include the empty
string, and in may cases, the set in infinite. A symbol is said to match the
current input, if the current input starts with an element of its language. Otherwise,
the symbol does not match. Example: a symbol  <literal>Integer</literal> typically
matches <literal>57...</literal>, but not <literal>xyz...</literal>. </para>

<figure>
<title>Symbols</title>
<programlisting>
Symbol              ::= StringSymbol | IdentifierSymbol ;
StringSymbol        ::= StringLiteral ;
IdentifierSymbol    ::= Identifier ;
Rule                ::= Subject "::=" RegExpr ";" ;
Subject             ::= Symbol ;
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Symbols</title>
<para>A symbol is a string symbol or an identifier symbol. The language of a
string symbol is defined implicitly by its string, whereas the language of
an identifier symbol is defined explicitly by one or more regular expressions.
Symbols are case-sensitive.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>String symbol</title>
<para>A string symbol is specified like a Java string literal. The language of a
string symbol is the string itself. For example, a string symbol <literal>"foo"</literal>
matches the string <literal>foo</literal>, nothing else. String symbols may contain all
escapes known from Java. It is an error to use different escapes to denote the same string.
For examples, Mork issues an error if you use both <literal>"foo\n"</literal>
and <literal>"foo\x0a"</literal> in a grammar file.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Identifier symbols</title>
<para>An identifier symbol is specified like a Java identifier. For any
identifier symbol used in the parser section, the must be at least one
rule. Let <literal>A ::= w1; A ::= w2; .. A ::= wn;</literal> be the set of all rules
with subject <literal>A</literal>. The language of <literal>A</literal> is defined by
the regular expression <literal>(w1) | (w2) ... | (wn)</literal>. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Rules</title>
<para>Rules define identifier symbols. The symbol on the left side of a
rule is called the subject of the rule. The subject must be an identifier
symbol. Regular expression in the parser may refer to any symbol, include
those defined later in the parser section and to symbols defined in the
scanner section. Regular expressions in the scanner section may not refer
to symbols in the parser section; they may refer to symbols in the scanner
section as long as not recursion is introduced. The same subject may be defined
by multiple rules, but all rules must be specified in the same section.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Inline symbols</title>
<para>A symbol defined in the scanner section and not referred from the parser section
is called an inline symbol. Inline symbols are used to simplify rules in the scanner section
(by factoring out common parts), they are not considered terminals. As a consequence, inline
symbols cannot be have attributes.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Conflicts</title>
<para>A conflict arises if a given input can be matched by two or more
symbols. The parser section is tested for conflicts at compile-time. If Mork
does not report conflicts, all conflicts, if any, have been resolved.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Conflicts on nonterminals</title>
<para>Mork issues an error message for all conflicts on nonterminal
symbols. The user must change the rules in the parser section to resolve
the conflict. There is currently no way to resolve conflicts by additional
declarations, e.g. operator precedence.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Conflicts on terminals</title>
<para>In contrast to nonterminals, all conflicts on terminal symbols are
resolved automatically. This conflict resolution follows the scheme used
most frequently by scanner tools: (1) if conflicting matches have different
lengths, the symbol with the longest match is applied; (2) otherwise, the
symbol defined first is applied. String symbols are considered to be defined
before identifier symbols. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Example</title>
<para>The input <literal>if</literal> can typically be matched by the symbol
<literal>Identifier</literal> and the string symbol <literal>"if"</literal>. Mork
matches the <literal>"if"</literal> symbols because its definition proceeds the
definition of the <literal>Identifier</literal> symbol.</para></formalpara>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Regular expression</title>

<para>Regular expressions define languages.</para>

<figure>
<title>Regular expression syntax</title>
<programlisting>
RegExpr             ::= Choice ;
Choice              ::= Choice "|" Sequence | Sequence ;
Sequence            ::= (Factor | Restriction)* ;
Restriction         ::= Factor "-" Factor;
Factor              ::= Operation | Reference | Range | "(" RegExpr ")" ;
Operation           ::= Star | Plus | Option | Times | Not ;

Star                ::= Factor "*" ;
Plus                ::= Factor "+" ;
Option              ::= Factor "?" ;
Times               ::= Factor ":" IntegerLiteral ;
Not                 ::= Factor "!" ;

Reference           ::= Symbol ;

Range               ::= Atom (".." Atom)? ;
Atom                ::= CharacterLiteral | Code ;
Code                ::= IntegerLiteral ;
</programlisting>
</figure>

<formalpara>
<title>Regular Expression</title>
<para>A regular expression defines a language, which is a set of strings.
In the parser section, regular expressions define context-free languages;
in the scanner section, regular expressions define regular expressions.
A regular expression is said to match a string if the string is an element
of the language. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Choice</title>
<para>A choice is a list of one or more sequences. A choice matches a string
if one of its sequences matches the string. Formally, the language of an
choice is the union of the languages of its sequences.
Example: <literal>A ::= "a" | "b";</literal> matches <literal>a</literal> or
<literal>b</literal>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Sequence</title>
<para>A sequence is a list of zero or more factors or restrictions. A sequence matches
any string that is the concatenation of strings matched by its factors. Formally,
the language of a sequence is the set of concatenations of element,
one element taken from any of its factors. An empty sequence matches
the empty string. Example: <literal>A ::= "a" "b";</literal> matches
<literal>ab</literal>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Restrictions</title>
<para>A restriction matches a string if the left factor matches the string and the right
factory does not match the string. This is useful, for example, to specify block
comments: <literal>comment ::= "/*" any* - (any* "*/" any*) "*/" ;</literal>.
Note that the syntax for restrictions does not permit <literal>A - B - C</literal> because
the precedence is not obvious. Use <literal>A - (B - C)</literal> or
<literal>(A - B) - C</literal> instead.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Operation</title>
<para>Operations are specified in postfix notation, giving priority to the
inner-most operator. The factor left of an operator is called its operand.
The following operations are available:</para></formalpara>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><formalpara><title>Plus</title>
  <para>A loop. Matches any string that is the concatenation of at
  least one string matched by the operand. Example:
  <literal>A ::= "a"+;</literal> matches <literal>a</literal>,
  <literal>aa</literal>, <literal>aaa</literal> etc.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>Star</title>
  <para>Optional loop; matches any string that is the concatenation
  of zero or more strings matched by the operand. Example:
  <literal>A ::= "a"*;</literal> matches empty string,
  <literal>a</literal>, <literal>aa</literal>, etc.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>Option</title>
  <para>Matches the empty string and any string matched by
  the operand. Example: <literal>A ::= "a"?;</literal> matches
  the empty string and <literal>a</literal>.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>Times</title>
  <para>Matches any string that is the concatenation of the given
  number of strings matched by the operand. Example:
  <literal>A ::= "a":4; </literal> matches <literal>aaaa</literal>.
  </para></formalpara></listitem>
<listitem><formalpara><title>Not</title>
  <para>matches the inverted character set of the operand. It is an error
  to apply this operator to an operand which is not a character set.
  A character set is a regular expression with only ranges and choices.
  Example: <literal>A ::= 'a'..'z'!;</literal> matches any character which
  is not a lower case letter. Advanced note: not inverts ranges, not languages;
  otherwise, <literal>'a'!</literal> would match any string except <literal>a</literal>,
  e.g. <literal>aa</literal>, <literal>aaa</literal>, etc. To invert languages
  use restrictions with an unmatchable left factory.</para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<formalpara>
<title>Reference</title>
<para>Matches any string matched by the specified symbol. It is an error
to reference parser symbols from the scanner section. References to scanner symbols
from the scanner section are valid as long as no recursion is introduced; these symbols
are automatically inlined, i.e. the symbol is replaced by it's definition.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Ranges</title>
<para>A range <literal>a..z</literal> matches any character <literal>x</literal> with
<literal>a &lt;= x &lt;= z</literal>. A single boundary range <literal>a</literal>
abbreviates the range <literal>a..a</literal>.  An empty range is a range where the upper
bound is smaller than its lower bound. Empty ranges are legal, they match nothing.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Atom</title>
<para>An atom matches the Unicode character it denotes. The character can
be specified by a character literal or by a Unicode number.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Translation into BNF</title>
<para>The following substitutions are used by Mork to turn regular expression
rules into plain context-free grammar rules. This is used to translate the
parser section into a context-free grammar. Substitutions have been chosen
to avoid nonterminal conflicts. In particular, the substitution of empty
loops <literal>Lst ::= Item*</literal> into <literal>Lst::= ;  Lst::= Item Lst;</literal>
is not used, even though the rules are less complicated.</para></formalpara>

<para>
<programlisting>
A ::= B | C   ->  A ::= B;   A ::= C;
A ::= B C? D; ->  A ::= B D; A ::= B C D;
A ::= B+;     ->  A ::= X;   X ::= X B;   X ::= B;
A ::= B*;     ->  A ::= B*?;
              ->  A ::= X;   A ::= ;      X ::= X B; X ::= B;
</programlisting></para>

<para>Notes: (1) The plus operator introduces new internal symbols.
(2) Negation is not mentioned here, because it is illegal in the parser
section.</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Example</title>
<para>The rule <literal>New ::= "new" Name "(" (Object ("," Object)*)? ")";</literal> is
internally turned to:
<programlisting>
New ::= "new" Name "(" Object ")" ;
New ::= "new" Name "(" Object "," Object ")" ;
New ::= "new" Name "(" Object Lst ")" ;
Lst ::= Lst "," Object ;
Lst ::= "," Object ;
</programlisting></para></formalpara>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Lexical structure</title>

<para>Grammar files essentially follow the lexical conventions of Java.
The only major difference is the <literal>EndOfLineComment</literal>.</para>

<figure>
<title>Lexical structure</title>
<programlisting>
WhiteSpace         ::= ( ' ' | '\t' | '\n' | '\f' | '\r' )+ ;
EndOfLineComment   ::= '/' '/' ('\n' | '\r')!* ('\n' | '\r') ;
TraditionalComment ::= '/' '*' ('*'! | '*' '/'!)* '*' '/' ;


IntegerLiteral     ::= '0'
                     | '1'..'9' '0'..'9'*
                     | '0' ('x'|'X')
                           ('0'..'9' | 'a'..'f' | 'A'..'F')+
                     | '0' ('0'..'7')+ ;

StringLiteral      ::= '"' (('\\' 0..65535)
                        | ('\\' | '"' | '\n' | '\r')!)+ '"' ;

CharacterLiteral   ::= '\'' (('\\' 0..65535) |
                           ('\\' |'\'' |'\n' | '\r')!)+ '\'' ;

Identifier ::=
   ( 0x0024..0x0024 | 0x0041..0x005a | 0x005f..0x005f |
     0x0061..0x007a | 0x00a2..0x00a5 | 0x00aa..0x00aa |
     0x00b5..0x00b5 | 0x00ba..0x00ba | 0x00c0..0x00d6 |
     0x00d8..0x00f6 | 0x00f8..0x00ff )
   ( 0x0000..0x0008 | 0x000e..0x001b | 0x0024..0x0024 |
     0x0030..0x0039 | 0x0041..0x005a | 0x005f..0x005f |
     0x0061..0x007a | 0x007f..0x009f | 0x00a2..0x00a5 |
     0x00aa..0x00aa | 0x00b5..0x00b5 | 0x00ba..0x00ba |
     0x00c0..0x00d6 | 0x00d8..0x00f6 | 0x00f8..0x00ff )* ;
</programlisting>
</figure>

<para>Differences from Java:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title><literal>EndOfLineComment</literal></title>
    <para><literal>EndOfLineComment</literal> start with the hash character <literal>#</literal>.
    Double slashes <literal>//</literal> known from Java <literal>EndOfLineComment</literal>s have
    a different meaning (they are used in paths).</para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Documentation comments</title>
    <para>Documentation comments are not distinguished from block comments.
    </para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>literals</title>
    <para>Floating-point and boolean literals are not available;
    type suffixes in <literal>IntegerLiterals</literal> are not available.
    </para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>keywords</title>
    <para>The set of keywords is different from Java. For examples, <literal>start</literal>
    is a keyword within specification files, whereas <literal>for</literal> is an identifier,
    not a keyword.</para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>identifier</title>
    <para>Identifiers are restricted to Unicode characters with a
    character code &lt;= 255.</para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Unicode preprocessing</title>
    <para>Prior to scanning, no Unicode preprocessing is performed. Thus,
    a token in general may not contain Unicode escapes. However, the
    definition of character and string literals has been extended to
    support Unicode escapes.</para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Scanner modes</title>

<para>A scanner mode is a set of terminals. Whenever matching a string, the scanner
matches only terminals in the current mode. Scanner modes are completely transparent, usually,
there is no need to care about them: at compile-time, scanner modes are computed automatically,
there is no need to manually declare scanner modes. At runtime, the parser automatically switches
to the appropriate scanner mode, there is no need to manually set the scanner mode. For most
grammar files, the resulting scanner has exactly one mode (containing all terminals). Mork's XML
grammar gives an example for a scanner with more than one mode. </para>

<para>TODO: more</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>XML syntax</title>

<formalpara>
<title>Attributes</title>
<para><indexterm><primary>Attributes</primary></indexterm>Unfortunately, the term attribute is
ambiguous: compiler tool attributes denote values attached to symbols, whereas XML attributes denote
name-value pairs attached to elements. The term attribute will be used throughout this manual if
the context allows to distinguish between compiler tool attributes and XML attributes. In most
cases attribute stands for compiler tool attributes - except in this section.</para></formalpara>

<para>XML syntax is specified by a document type definition. It is comprised of
a list of element declarations and attribute definitions. A detailed description
can be found in chapter 3 of the XML specification
(<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml">http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml</ulink>).
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Naming convention</title>
<para>My naming convention for DTD files is as follows: The base name is the
name of the language specified in the file. The first letter is lowercase
because this is what I know from DocBook. The file name extension is
<literal>.dtd</literal> (all lower case on every platform). Examples:
<literal>docbook.dtd</literal> for a syntax definition of DocBook,
<literal>config.dtd</literal> for the syntax of configuration files.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Status</title>
<para>Support for XML syntax was introduced in Mork 0.3.0 and is in its early
stages. Here are the major current limitations:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>no mixed content</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>no any content</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>no namespace support</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Element content is fully validated, but attribute content is not.</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Mapping</title>
<para>Mapper files refer to elements by the element's name. Attributes are
referenced by the associated element, an dollar sign, and the attribute name.
Example: given that DTD fragment
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  <!ELEMENT foo (someElements)>
  <!ATTLIST foo bar CDATA #IMPLIED>
]]></programlisting>
you can map the element <literal>foo</literal> and its attribute <literal>bar</literal> like this:
<programlisting>
  foo      => Constructor1;
  foo$bar  => Constructor2;
</programlisting>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Terminals</title>
<para>Attributes are considered terminals, thus, you can use <literal>[text]</literal> to obtain
the attribute's value. In addition there is a terminal <literal>PCDATA</literal> that matches the
content of elements defined as <literal>PCDATA</literal>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Start symbol</title>
<para>The first symbol defined in DTD file is the start symbol. </para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>Use the <literal>-lst</literal> option to check the parser generated by Mork.
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Example</title>
<para>The <literal>config</literal> example in <literal>mork/examples/config</literal> demonstrates
most of the available features.</para></formalpara>

</sect1>

</chapter>
